International Workers Order (IWO) Records 5276
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Ohio, 1947-1948 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  Correspondence form an organizer relating experiences of members dropping out because of fear; financial problems in lodges - Milgrom writes that expenses have to be cut; "Minutes of the City Central" (Cleveland), 2/10/47; from a member in Akron requesting
- Pennsylvania, 1938-1949 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  List of Anthracite Districts by lodge number, giving Secretary's name and number of members, June 1938; "Proceedings of the Anthracite Area, 5th District Convention of the IWO, November 9-10, 1940" and "Resolutions of the Anthracite Area, 1940"; correspond
- Philadelphia, 1944-1949 (Box 57, Folder 10)
  Correspondence between Sol Rotenberg, Executive Secretary, Eastern Pennsylvania District Committee and Sam Milgrom re election campaign; recruitment of Negroes; Social Security campaign; National Health Act legislation; correspondence and news clippings re
- Philadelphia, 1944-1949 (Box 57, Folder 11)
- Pittsburgh, 1944-1950 (Box 58, Folder 1)
  Correspondence re recruitment drive and 9 p. "Draft Plan - Western Pennsylvania Membership Drive" by Sam Milgrom; memo on Christmas parties for miners' families; statistics on membership campaign tour; "Report on Western Pennsylvania Drive," n.d.; and rou
- West Virginia, 1941-1944 (Box 58, Folder 2)
  Correspondence re financial difficulties with operation of Lodge 624 in Charleston; and routine.
- Wisconsin, 1945 (Box 58, Folder 3)
  Correspondence re obtaining a charter for Milwaukee, Wisconsin; dissolving the Italian lodge in Milwaukee; building up the City Central; list of Wisconsin lodges.
- General lodges, 1938-1945 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  Correspondence with Immigrant and Naturalization Services re becoming naturalized citizens whether or not members of IWO; re IWO license in state of Ohio as fraternal beneficiary society; statistics on membership by lodge # (1944); program planning for bu
- General Lodges, 1946-1948 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  Statistical sheets, "Membership Campaign" gives number of members by Lodge number; "Membership in Negro Concentration Lodges" - statistics by Lodge number, also gives location; draft program of "Summerdale Leadership Training School"; "Minutes of General
- Carpatho-Russian Society, 1942-1949 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  Substantial amount of correspondence from Scranton, Pennsylvania, Bridgeport, Connecticut and Gary, Indiana most of which I cannot translate - The few letters in English contain certain routine correspondence re death and sick claim benefits, meeting arrangement
- Carpatho-Russian Society, 1942-1949 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  Substantial amount of correspondence from Scranton, Pennsylvania, Bridgeport, Connecticut and Gary, Indiana most of which I cannot translate - The few letters in English contain certain routine correspondence re death and sick claim benefits, meeting
- Carpatho-Russian Society, 1942-1949 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Carpatho-Russian Society, 1942-1949 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Carpatho-Russian Society, 1942-1949 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Cervantes Fraternal Society - Miscellaneous, 1944-1947 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  7 page mss., "The Hispanic American Section from January 1940 to January 1944;" statistical sheet re membership of Society for l946.
- Cervantes Fraternal Society - Lodge 4792 (New York City), 1947-1951 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  Spanish. The few letters in English re sick benefits for members; dues payments; list of members.
- Cervantes Fraternal Society - Lodge 4792 (New York City), 1947-1951 (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Cervantes Fraternal Society - Lodge 4792 (New York City), 1947-1951 (Box 58, Folder 4)
- Cervantes Fraternal Society - Lodge 4792 (New York City), 1947-1951 (Box 58, Folder 5)
- Cervantes Fraternal Society - Convention, 1947 (Box 58, Folder 6)
  Includes 3 page, "Short Report on the Highlights of the National Convention of the Cervantes Fraternal Society of the IWO, June 13-14, 1947, New York City." Remainder of folder in Spanish - (minutes, constitution).
- Croatian - American Section, 1940-1952 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  Correspondence re problems with personnel and the location of headquarters; 5 page report in letter from to Bedacht from N.S. Rajkrovich, Secretary of Section giving detailed report of developments and activities from 1940 - January 1944; sheets re member
- Czechoslovakian Workers Club, 1933-1936 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  2 items - unable to translate
- Douglass-Lincoln Fraternal Society, 1949-1950 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  Includes scattered minutes; 4 pages "Remarks to Thirty Party Platform. Hearings Committee, Philadelphia, July 21, 1948" re health, wages, housing of Negroes; memo re Societies forming a Fraternal Committee of the American Labor Party; Report of Lodge 816
- Finnish Workers Federation, 1941-1946 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  Includes pamphlet "The Unity & Merger of the Finnish Workers Federation with the IWO," January 1941. 10 pages; 5 page report to Bedacht covering the period 1942-44 of Activities of Finnish Workers Federation; 2 page report to Bedacht, January 1946 re t
- Greek-American Fraternal Society, 1944-1956 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  Includes constitution; Report (3 pages) on the development of Greek-American Section & Activities, and political problems in Greece; list of members of National Committee of the Hellenic-American Fraternal Society; correspondence.
- Hungarian-American Section (Box 10, Folder 6)
  Constitution (n.d.); "Hungarian-Americans, Who Are They?" by John Roman, IWO, n.d., 48 pages; 4 page report re membership, United Front Actions, 1946 re issue of the Hungarian minority in Czechoslovakia, aid to new Hungarian democracy, American Hungarian
- Hungarian-American Section (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Italian-Garibaldi American Fraternal Society, 1937-1943 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  With Congressman Vito Marcantonio re Society's political support and giving his assurance to do "all in my power ... to end Hitlerism"; letter to "Supreme Order Sons of Italy in America" form National Commission of Italian Americans Section IWO re joining
- Italian-Garibaldi American Fraternal Society, 1944-1947 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  Letter to War Department in support of funds being sent to Sicily, 2/14/44; political election (1944); to Congressmen re Marcantonio' s resolution to recognize Italy as an Ally (1945); routine with Congressman Vito Marcantonio; financial; membership recruit
- Italian-Garibaldi American Fraternal Society, 1948-1951 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  Several issues of Society's Monthly Letter; Correspondence re "defense of the Order"; memo (7 pages) re Shipka's report to General Council concerning the attack on the Order; correspondence re member in Arnold, Pennsylvania, "framed" due to his membership
- Italian-Garibaldi American Fraternal Society (Box 10, Folder 11)
  10 page "Prospectus for an Italian-American Community Center in East Harlem"; and routine.
- Italian-Garibaldi American Fraternal Society (Box 58, Folder 7)
- Italian-Garibaldi American Fraternal Society (Box 58, Folder 8)
- Italian-Garibaldi American Fraternal Society (Box 58, Folder 9)
- Polish-American Section, 1940-1946 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  Correspondence re suspension of members of Lodge 3544 for not abiding by constitution of the Order; 4 page memo to Max Bedacht from Boleslaw Gebert, President (Polish-American Section) re proposals for building membership, 6/30/42, "the best possible base
- Polish-American Section, 1947-1957 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  3 page "Extracts from the Speech delivered by President Gebert at the Conference of the Polonia Society ..., December 14-15, 1947" re fight against fascism, supporting the labor movement, and political support; 8 page description of various Polish organization
- Polish-American Section (Box 11, Folder 3)
  Membership Record sheets by lodge number.
- Polish-American Section (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Polish-American Section (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Romanian-American Fraternal Society, 1944-1946 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  10 page "Informative Notes on the Situation in Lodge 4503 - Dearborn, Michigan," re religious situation and lodge involvement; membership statistics; 4 page report (in letter form) to Bedacht from Mary Mila, describes political efforts, war efforts, memb3
- Russian National Mutual Aid Society - Convention, 1927 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  Convention material in Russian including delegates list, proceedings, correspondence, delegate instructions.
- Russian National Mutual Aid Society - Convention, 1929 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  Proceedings in Russian.
- Russian National Mutual Aid Society - Convention, 1930 (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Russian National Mutual Aid Society - Convention, 1933 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  Minutes in Russian and English - discusses unemployment, unity with IWO, Comrade Radsy - representative from Russian Section, Communist Party addressed the delegates, White Guardists, political militancy, International Labor Defense, organizing women's, c
- Russian National Mutual Aid Society - Convention, 1935 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  Proceedings and pamphlet in Russian.
- Russian National Mutual Aid Society - Certificates and Licenses, 1928-1934 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  License from Division of Insurance, Ohio, certificates from Pennsylvania, Insurance Department.
- Russian Section, IWO - Reports and Proceedings, 1931-1950 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  Proceedings and finances of Russian Section, in Russian.
- Russian Section, IWO - Reports and Proceedings, 1936-1938 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  Plenum proceedings of the Central Committee, Russian Section, IWO, 1936; Report of Daniela Kazoushchika at the meeting of the Russian Section, IWO - 1938; proceedings of Russian Section, IWO, 1938, in Russian.
- Russian Section, IWO - Reports and Proceedings, 1940-1944 (Box 59, Folder 1)
  Report of the Russian Section, IWO to the 5th National Convention, IWO, in Russian.
- Russian Section - Lodge 3057, 1946-1917 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  Sick Benefit correspondence expulsion correspondence, and routine, mostly in Russian.
- Russian Section - Lodge 3103, 1947 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  Sick Benefit correspondence in Russian, 1947.
- Russian Section, IWO - Miscellaneous, 1944-1947 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  Memos, speech, certificate of Incorporation of United American Societies for Soviet Relief, Inc., 1944-47; correspondence in Russian, unable to translate, 1945.
- Serbian-American Federation, IWO - Correspondence, 1943-1945 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  Routine correspondence; report on progress since 1940; plan for recruiting drive; correspondence re Yugoslav Relief, Peter Vukcevich correspondence.
- Serbian-American Federation, IWO - Correspondence, 1946-1947 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  Form letter re Tag Day Campaign; pledged projects, correspondence re Yugoslav relief and routine; copy of letter to Max Bedacht from Edward C. Carter re American Society for Russian Relief; memos; N. Baltich correspondence.
- Serbian-American Federation, IWO - Miscellaneous (Box 13, Folder 6)
  Leaflet from American Committee for Yugoslav Relief; IWO bulletin of Activities Aids; newsletter; minutes of the regular bi-monthly meeting of Executive Committee of the American Association for Reconstruction in Yugoslavia, November 30, 1946, at Hotel Ro
- Serbian-American Federation, IWO, 1938-1947 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  In Serbian, includes Nikola Baltich correspondence.
- Serbian-American Federation, IWO, 1938-1947 (Box 13, Folder 8)
- Serbian-American Federation, IWO, 1938-1947 (Box 13, Folder 9)
- Serbian-American Federation, IWO, 1938-1947 (Box 59, Folder 2)
- Serbian-American Federation, IWO, 1938-1947 (Box 59, Folder 3)
- Slovak Workers Society, Pre-IWO, 1922-1925 (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Slovak Workers Society - Constitutions and By-laws, 1915-1938 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Slovak Workers Society - Convention Reports, 1923-1947 (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Slovak Workers Society - Convention Reports, 1923-1947 (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Slovak Workers Society - Convention Reports, 1923-1947 (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Slovak Workers Society - Reports to IWO Conventions, 1933-1944 (Box 59, Folder 4)
- Slovak Workers Society - Bulletin, 1917-1933 (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Slovak Workers Society - Bulletin, 1917-1933 (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Slovak Workers Society - Correspondence, 1943-1947 (Box 15, Folder 3)
- Slovak Workers Society - History of Slovaks, 1938-1941 (Box 15, Folder 4)
- Slovak Workers Society - Miscellaneous, 1945-1947 (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Ukrainian Section, IWO - Constitutions, 1938-1945 (Box 15, Folder 6)
- Ukrainian Section, IWO - Proceedings and Reports, 1935-1950 (Box 15, Folder 7)
- Ukrainian Section, IWO - Correspondence, 1944-1951 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  form letters; letter from M. Bonn (Pittsburgh) discussing John Derkascz incident; routine; and untranslatable correspondence memo form Frank Ilchuk, President re Ukrainian folk festivals.
- Ukrainian Section, IWO - Miscellaneous, 1926-1950 (Box 59, Folder 5)
  Unable to translate, includes itinerary of lecture tour - Brother Riback
- Abraham Lincoln School, 1945 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  Documents re summer school in Chicago for IWO members.
- Aliens, 1941-1942 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  Pamphlets, releases, clipping (some published by the American Committee for Protection of Foreign Born).
- American Labor Party, 1949 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  memo re national registration campaign proposals and fund raising.
- Atlantic Charter, 1942 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  Includes official text of White House statement and articles.
- Camp Association, 1939 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  Includes proposed constitution of the IWO Camp Association, form letter and list of members to be called to Camp Committee meeting.
- Civil Defense, 1941-1942 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  Pamphlets; news clippings; memo re volunteers; statement by General Executive Board, IWO on responsibilities.
- Clippings, 1942 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  Miscellaneous clippings.
- Committees - Administration Committee, 1941 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  Form letter re dues paid by social members may be applied to initiation fee.
- Committees - Appeals Committee, 1940-1941 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  Minutes of the National Appeals Committee discusses various issues and cases brought before the Committee by lodges.
- Committees - City School Committee, 1938-1943 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  Correspondence re annual census of Jewish Schools in New York; statistics on the number of pupils; and generally routine correspondence.
- Committees - Committee for the Freedom of Sam Milgrom, 1952-1953 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  Broadsides, form letters, releases re the unconstitutional denial of bail in the McCarran Act deportation of Sam Milgrom.
- Committees - Executive Committee, 1941 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  Includes May 5, 1941 "Minutes of the Executive Committee," 2 pages.
- Committees - IWO Policyholders Protective Committee, 1952-1953 (Box 16, Folder 13)
  Form letters, releases, brochures, statement, memos re the Attorney-General's McCarran Act citation ("Communist-front" organization).
- Committees - National Education Committee, 1941 (Box 16, Folder 14)
  "Minutes of the National Education Committee (IWO), May 7, 1941," 2 pages.
- Committees - National Women's Committee, 1941 (Box 16, Folder 15)
  Routine form letter; minutes, 4/26, 5/7, 9/3, 1941.
- Committees - New York City Central Committee, 1941 (Box 16, Folder 16)
  Routine form letter re plans for May Day celebration.
- Committees - Organization Committee, 1940-1941 (Box 16, Folder 17)
  Includes minutes of the committee and "Report to the Organization Committee and Plan of Concentration for Negro Work," by M. Moran Weston, 4 pages.
- Committees - Social Security Committee, 1941-1946 (Box 16, Folder 18)
  Report of income (1941) and release February 1946.
- Committees - State Legislative Committee (Box 16, Folder 19)
  3 page release published by the Committee re legislative bills before Congress.
- Consumers, 1941-1944 (Box 16, Folder 20)
  2 publications re consumer information (not published by IWO).
- Cultural Activities, 1943-1951 (Box 16, Folder 21)
  Includes minutes, reports, correspondence, broadsides, clippings, release re various cultural events.
- Cultural Activities - Abner Greentour, 1945 (Box 16, Folder 22)
  Correspondence generally re plans for meetings in various cities; broadside re "I Am An American Day."
- Film Division, 1944-1945 (Box 16, Folder 23)
  Financial reports, reports of activities.
- Fraternal Outlook - Memos, 1942 (Box 16, Folder 24)
  Routine form letters
- Fraternal Welfare Fund, 1948 (Box 16, Folder 25)
  Form letter re aid for aged members of the Order
- Front Line Fighters Fund, 1940-1944 (Box 16, Folder 26)
  Includes correspondence, articles, pamphlets re "fund that provides aid in a spirit of patriotic devotion and international solidarity"; correspondence with President's War Relief Control Board re rules and regulations of fund raising activities by organizations
- Front Line Fighters Fund, 1940-1944 (Box 60, Folder 1)
  Includes correspondence, articles, pamphlets re "fund that provides aid in a spirit of patriotic devotion and international solidarity"; correspondence with President's War Relief Control Board re rules and regulations of fund raising activities by
- Front Line Fighters Fund, 1940-1944 (Box 60, Folder 2)
- Health, 1942-1943 (Box 60, Folder 3)
  Includes publications, clippings, bulletins, (non-IWO) re general public and workers' health during wartime.
- Health and Social Security Campaign, 1945-1946 (Box 60, Folder 4)
  4 page resolution on organization of the Campaign adopted at IWO Conference.
- History, 1947 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  Includes typed drafts of various sections of Part 1 "History of the IWO and Role of the Fraternal Movement in the U.S."; Part 2 "Insurance"; Part 3 "The Lodge Program."
- History, 1947 (Box 17, Folder 2)
- History, 1947 (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Home for the Aged (Box 17, Folder 4)
  5 page manuscript, "IWO Home for the Aged" re plans and preparations for a home for aged members of IWO.
- I Am An American Day, 1945 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  Correspondence; release; lists of supporters by Society; brochure, "Thoughts of an American" by Frank Sinatra.
- IWO Defense Fund, 1948-1950 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  Correspondence; handwritten notes; form letters re raising funds "to defend our beloved Order against the unconstitutional, slanderous attacks made against us by Attorney-General Clark"; also includes financial/statistical information - report "Present St
- Ingram Children's Education and Welfare Fund, 1948-1949 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  Correspondence releases re raising funds for the education and care of the children of Rosa Ingram, Negro mother of 12 children who, with 2 of her sons, was sentenced to a life sentence for the self-defense slaying of a white sharecropper.
- Ingram Children's Education and Welfare Fund, 1948-1949 (Box 17, Folder 8)
- Ingram Children's Education and Welfare Fund, 1948-1949 (Box 17, Folder 9)
- Jewish History Week, 1945-1946 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  Includes handwritten notes, correspondence, minutes, 28 page "Verbatim Report of Proceedings at a Meeting Against Anti-Semitism and for a Jewish History Week - Under the Auspices of New Masses," 1945.
- Labor - Miscellaneous, 1945-1947 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  Newspaper clippings, information sheet on proposed labor legislation, publications, form letter.
- Legal Correspondence, 1944-1950 (Box 17, Folder 12)
  Generally correspondence with Lee Pressman, IWO Attorney, and others re income matters, incorporation certificates, various court cases, naturalization proceedings, financial matters and other legal routine.
- Legal Correspondence, 1951-1953 (Box 17, Folder 13)
- Legal Deportation and Loyalty Cases, 1948-1953 (Box 60, Folder 5)
  Includes correspondence, releases, form letters, court brief re Gwinn Amendment (Housing) occupancy of building if "subversive"; legal correspondence re members requesting assistance in fighting deportation and concern re possibilities of revoking citizen
- Legal - Loyalty Petitions, 1947-1948 (Box 60, Folder 6)
  Signed resolutions form lodges all around the country condemning the arbitrary, scandalous declaration of the Attorney-General who questioned the IWO's loyalty.
- Legal - New York State Insurance Department, 1949-1950 (Box 60, Folder 7)
  "Report on Examination of the International Workers Order, Inc." by James B. Haley, Opinion and Findings of the Deputy Superintendent, Brief to Dismiss Proceedings.
- Legal - Massachusetts, 1938 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  17 page legal document, "Report of Examination re: Use of Corporate Funds of the IWO, Inc.," submitted in Boston, Massachusetts, re sending corporate funds to support the Spanish government, using funds for publication of political magazine, and using fun
- May Day, 1946-1947 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  Publications and clippings.
- Membership and Lodge Membership Records, 1952-1953 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  Sheets re membership - new, reinstatements, expiration, by Society; also information re discontinued lodges.
- Membership Campaign, 1944 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  [15] page document, "Vital Information on 6th Pre-Convention Membership Campaign, March 1 to June 15, 1944," (IWO National Organization Department).
- Membership Department - Reinstatements, 1952-1953 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  Correspondence with members requesting to be reinstated under special plan announced by IWO whereby members who had dropped out over a 3 year period could apply by paying only 3 months back dues along with a signed health statement.
- Membership Department - Reinstatements, 1952-1953 (Box 18, Folder 6)
- Membership Department - Reinstatements, 1952-1953 (Box 18, Folder 7)
- Membership Department - Reinstatements, 1952-1953 (Box 18, Folder 8)
- Membership Department - Reinstatements, 1952-1953 (Box 18, Folder 9)
- Membership Department - Reinstatements, 1952-1953 (Box 18, Folder 10)
- Membership Drive, 1939 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  Includes report, manual for builders, 10 page "Why and How the IWO Organizes - Its Grand Campaign of 1939."
- Membership Drive - Pennsylvania, 1945 (Box 18, Folder 12)
  9 page document "Draft Plan - Western Pennsylvania Membership Drive" re strengthening the Order in the mine, steel and aluminum industries, strengthening existing lodges, etc.
- Membership - General, 1938-1949 (Box 18, Folder 13)
  Includes completed questionnaires from lodges re number of members, what language, average attendance, women members, and of special interest, which are replies when asked for General Remarks concerning experiences or opinions on any of the problems of th
- Membership - General, 1938-1949 (Box 18, Folder 14)
- Membership - General, 1938-1949 (Box 18, Folder 15)
- Membership Records, 1938-1940 (Box 61, Folder 1)
  Statistical sheets giving membership information by Sections.
- Membership Records, 1938-1940 (Box 61, Folder 2)
- Membership - Social Members, 1947-1950 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  Sheets stamped "social members," giving date, names and lodge number.
- Membership - Social Members, 1947-1950 (Box 19, Folder 2)
- Membership - Weekly Recruiting Reports, 1938 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  Statistical charts re weekly reports on District recruiting and recruiting of sections.
- Memoranda - General, 1941 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  General memos re office supplies, etc.
- Memorial Day, 1945 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  Lists of members killed in World War II, newspaper clippings.
- Miscellaneous (Box 19, Folder 6)
  Miscellaneous manuscript drafts re U.S. Dilemma in the Middle East, Guiding Policy for the Communists in their leadership and work in the IWO; memo on Editorial policy of Fraternal Outlook; manuscript, "Activities of the Order on Behalf of Labor," 16 page
- Mundt-Nixon Bill, 1948 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  Includes 4 page "Analysis of the Mundt Police State Bill (HR 5852)" by IWO; clippings; transcript of proceedings of IWO National Conference to Defeat the Mundt Bill; copies of the bill; form letter from President Kent to all lodges and miscellaneous.
- National Women's Committee, 1941 (Box 19, Folder 8)